Finding Aid for Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers (University of Michigan) records, 1990-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers (University of Michigan) records 1990-1999 1995-1997
University of Michigan. Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers.
0.5 linear feet
2011144 Bimu 2
University of Michigan organization with the aim of promoting educational and professional opportunities for Hispanic engineering and science students, as well as their graduation and recruitment. It operated under the Society of Minority Engineering Students organization on campus.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the unit in 1997 (donor 8639 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers was a student chapter of the national professional organization of the same name. The national chapter had been established in 1974 in California. The local University of Michigan, Ann Arbor chapter was recognized in 1992 and operates as part of the Society of Minority Engineering Students organization on campus.
The UM SHPE chapter's mission is to serve and empower the Hispanic engineering community; to promote academic excellence, professional and personal development, leadership, and service. They aspire to achieve this by "providing resources to assist them (UM Hispanic community) during their college career. Such resources include workshops and general body meetings, where various companies speak about career opportunities, provide resume and interviewing skills workshops, and provide students with a better understanding of what life could be like after graduation."
The SHPE chapter goals are:
To achieve a sense of community among Hispanic engineering and applied sciences students at the University of Michigan and other SHPE student chapters.
To unite and organize Latino Engineering students based on their various needs.
To promote professional as well as cultural awareness by means of social and intellectual interaction.
To seek out and recruit potential Hispanic engineering and applied students.
To improve the retention of Hispanic engineering and applied sciences students at the University of Michigan.
To assist University faculty and staff to learn about and appreciate Hispanic/ Latin American culture.
The chapter's mission, goals and additional cited in formation was taken from the UM SHPE website: http://www.shpe.studentorgs.umich.edu/ (accessed November 2011).
SCOPE CONTENT
Subjects:
Minority College Students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Students--Societies, etc.; Society of Minority Engineers (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. College of Engineering.
- Records
  The Records series comprises official documentation produced by the Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers (SHPE) as part of their work as the University of Michigan chapter of this organization from 1991 to 1999, while the bulk of it is the product of the chapter's work from 1995 to 1997. The material includes the constitution of the organization, the SHPE student chapter handbook, meeting related documentation such as agendas and minutes, as well as information on members, officers and membership. It also contains documents concerning event planning and collaboration with other organizations. The series is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Calendar of Events, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Constitution (Box 1)
  - Emails (printouts), 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - End of the year report, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - News clippings and photographs, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Officer and Member Information, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Programming Task Force (Multi-Ethnic Student Affairs), 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - SHPE Performance Surveys, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - SHPE Student Chapter Handbook, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
- Publications
  The Publications series includes materials such as newsletters and brochures from 1990 to 1997.
  - Newsletters and brochures, 1990-1997 (Box 1)
- Conference and Awards Materials
  The Conference and Awards series includes awards received by the organization or its officers and materials from SHPE national and Society of Minority Engineering Students local conferences attended from 1995 to 1997. The series is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Forums and workshops (Box 1)
  - SHPE Awards, 1997 (Box 1)
  - SHPE Conference, 1997 (Box 1)
  - SMES Conference and Banquet Materials, 1996, 1997 (Box 1)
- Résumé books
  The Résumé books series contains sections of résumé books compiled by the Society of Minority Engineering Students at the University of Michigan for industry representatives to promote minority student employment.
  - SMES Résumé book, 1990-1991, 1995 (Box 1)